<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_drama.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_drama.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Arcadia</title>
            <author>Tom Stoppard</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Text prepared for LEAF-Writer workshop by LEAF team.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
            <titlePage>
               <docTitle>
                  <titlePart>Arcadia</titlePart>
               </docTitle>
               <docAuthor>Tom Stoppard</docAuthor>
            </titlePage>
            <castList>
               <castItem xml:id="croom">Lady Croom</castItem>
               <castItem xml:id="thomasina">Thomasina Coverly</castItem>
               <castItem xml:id="septimus">Septimus Hodge</castItem>
               <castItem xml:id="noakes">Richard Noakes</castItem>
               <castItem xml:id="augustus">Augustus Croom</castItem>
            </castList>
         
      </front>

<body>         <note>Excerpt from Act 2</note>

         <stage>Thomasina thumps the book down on the table.</stage>

         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Well! Just as I said! Newton's machine which would knock our atoms from cradle to
               grave by the laws of motion is incomplete! Determinism leaves the road at every
               corner, as I knew all along, and the cause is very likely hidden in this gentleman's
               observation.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab> Of what?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>The action of bodies in heat.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Is this geometry?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>This? No, I despise geometry! <stage>(Touching the dahlias she adds, almost to
                  herself.)</stage> The Chater would overthrow the Newtonian system in a
               weekend.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>Geometry, Hobbes assures us in the Leviathan, is the only science God has been
               pleased to bestow on mankind.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>And what does he mean by it?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>Mr Hobbes or God?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>I am sure I do not know what either means by it.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Oh, pooh to Hobbes! Mountains are not pyramids and trees are not cones. God must
               love gunnery and architecture if Euclid is his only geometry. There is another
               geometry which I am engaged in discovering by trial and error, am I not,
               Septimus?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>Trial and error perfectly describes your enthusiasm, my lady.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>How old are you today?</ab></sp> 
         
         <sp><speaker>Thomasina:</speaker> <ab>Sixteen years and eleven months, mama, and three
               weeks.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Sixteen years and eleven months. We must have you married before you are educated
               beyond eligibility.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>I am going to marry Lord Byron.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Are you? He did not have the manners to mention it.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>You have spoken to him?!</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Certainly not.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Where did you see him?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <stage>(With some bitterness)</stage>
            <ab>Everywhere.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Did you, Septimus?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>At the Royal Academy where I had the honour to accompany your mother and Count
               Zelinsky.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>What was Lord Byron doing?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Posing.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <stage>(Tactfully)</stage>
            <ab>He was being sketched during his visit. by the Professor of Painting ... Mr
               Fuseli.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>There was more posing at the pictures than in them. His companion likewise reversed
               the custom of the Academy that the ladies viewing wear more than the ladies viewed -
               well, enough! Let him be hanged there for a Lamb. I have enough with Mr Noakes, who
               is to a garden what a bull is to a china shop.</ab>
            <stage>(This as Noakes enters.)</stage>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>The Emperor of Irregularity!</ab>
         </sp>
         <stage>(She settles down to drawing the diagram which is to be the third item in the
            surviving portfolio.)</stage>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Mr Noakes!</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>Your ladyship -</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>What have you done to me!</ab>
         </sp>

         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>Everything is satisfactory, I assure you. A little behind, to be sure, but my dam
               will be repaired within the month -</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab><stage>(Banging the table)</stage> Hush! <stage>(In the silence, the steam engine
                  thumps in the distance.)</stage> Can you hear, Mr Noakes?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab><stage>(Pleased and proud)</stage> The Improved Newcomen steam pump - the only one
               in England!</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>That is what I object to. If everybody had his own I would bear my portion of the
               agony without complaint. But to have been singled out by the only Improved Newcomen
               steam pump in England, this is hard, sir, this is not to be borne.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>Your lady-</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>And for what? My lake is drained to a ditch for no purpose I can understand, unless
               it be that snipe and curlew have deserted three counties so that they may be shot in
               our swamp. What you painted as forest is a mean plantation, your greenery is mud,
               your waterfall is wet mud, and your mount is an opencast mine for the mud that was
               lacking in the dell. <stage>(Pointing through the window.)</stage> What is that
               cowshed?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>The hermitage, my lady?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>It is a cowshed.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker> Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>Madam, it is, I assure you, a very habitable cottage, properly founded and drained,
               two rooms and a closet under a slate roof and a stone chimney -</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>And who is to live in it?</ab></sp> 
         
         <sp><speaker>Noakes:</speaker> <ab>Why, the hermit.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Where is he?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>Madam?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>You surely do not supply a hermitage without a hermit?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>Indeed, madam-</ab>
         </sp>

         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Come, come, Mr Noakes. If I am promised a fountain I expect it to come with water.
               What hermits do you have?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>I have no hermits, my lady.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Not one? I am speechless.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>I am sure a hermit can be found. One could advertise.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Advertise?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>In the newspapers.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>But surely a hermit who takes a newspaper is not a hermit in whom one can have
               complete confidence.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab>I do not know what to suggest, my lady.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>Is there room for a piano?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab><stage>(Baffled)</stage> A piano?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>We are intruding here - this will not do, Mr Hodge. Evidently, nothing is being
               learned. <stage>(To Noakes)</stage> Come along, sir!</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Mr Noakes - bad news from Paris!</ab></sp> 
         
         <sp><speaker>Noakes:</speaker> <ab>Is it the Emperor Napoleon?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>No. <stage>(She tears the page off her drawing block with her 'diagram' on
                  it.)</stage> It concerns your heat engine. Improve it as you will, you can never
               get out of it what you put in. It repays eleven pence in the shilling at most. The
               penny is for this author's thoughts. (She gives the diagram to Septimus who looks at
               it.)</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Noakes:</speaker>
            <ab><stage>(Baffled again)</stage> Thank you, my lady.</ab>
         </sp>
         <stage>(Noakes goes out into the garden.)</stage>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab><stage>(To Septimus)</stage> Do you understand her?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>No.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Lady Croom:</speaker>
            <ab>Then this business is over. I was married at seventeen. Ce soir il faut qu'on parle
               francais,je te demande, Thomasina, as a courtesy to the Count. Wear your green
               velvet, please, I will send Briggs to do your hair. Sixteen and eleven months . . .!
                  <stage>(She follows Noakes out of view.)</stage></ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Lord Byron was with a lady?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>Yes.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Huh!</ab>
         </sp>
         <stage>(Now Septimus retrieves his book from Thomasina. He turns the pages, and also
            continues to study Thomasina's diagram. He strokes the tortoise absently as he reads,
            Thomasina takes up pencil and paper and starts to draw Septimus with Plautus.)</stage>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>Why does it mean Mr Noakes's engine pays eleven pence in the shilling? Where does he
               say it?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Nowhere. I noticed it by the way. I cannot remember now. Septimus: Nor is he
               interested by determinism -</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Oh . .. yes. Newton's equations go forwards and backwards, they do not care which
               way. But the heat equation cares very much, it goes only one way. That is the reason
               Mr Noakes's engine cannot give the power to drive Mr Noakes's engine.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus: </speaker>
            <ab>Everybody knows that.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>Yes, Septimus, they know it about engines!</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab><stage>(Pause. He looks at his watch.)</stage> A quarter to twelve. For your essay
               this week, explicate your diagram.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>I cannot. I do not know the mathematics.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>Without mathematics, then.</ab>
         </sp>
         <stage>(Thomasina has continued to draw. She tears the top page from her drawing pad and
            gives it to Septimus.)</stage>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Thomasina:</speaker>
            <ab>There. I have made a drawing of you and Plautus.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <stage>(Looking at it)</stage>
            <ab>Excellent likeness. Not so good of me.</ab>
            <stage>(Thomasina laughs, and leaves the room. Augustus appears at the garden door. His
               manner cautious and diffident. Septimus does not notice him for a moment. Septimus
               gathers his papers together.)</stage>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker> Augustus:</speaker>
            <ab>Sir .. .</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>My lord . . . ?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Augustus:</speaker>
            <ab>I gave you offence, sir, and I am sorry for it.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>I took none, my lord, but you are kind to mention it.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Augustus:</speaker>
            <ab>I would like to ask you a question, Mr Hodge. <stage>(Pause.)</stage> You have an
               elder brother, I dare say, being a Septimus?</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>Yes, my lord. He lives in London. He is the editor of a newspaper, the Piccadilly
               Recreation. <stage>(Pause.)</stage> Was that your question?</ab>
         </sp>
         <stage>(Augustus, evidently embarrassed about something, picks up the drawing of
            Septimus.)</stage>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Augustus:</speaker>
            <ab>No. Oh ... it is you? ... I would like to keep it. <stage>(Septimus inclines his
                  head in assent.)</stage> There are things a fellow cannot ask his friends. Carnal
               things. My sister has told me ... my sister believes such things as I cannot, I
               assure you, bring myself to repeat.</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Septimus:</speaker>
            <ab>You must not repeat them, then. The walk between here and dinner will suffice to put
               us straight, if we stroll by the garden. It is an easy business. And then I must rely
               on you to correct your sister's state of ignorance.</ab>
         </sp>
         <stage>(A commotion is heard outside - Bernard's loud voice in a sort of agony.)</stage>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Bernard:</speaker>
            <ab><stage>(outside the door)</stage> Oh no - no - no - oh, bloody hell! -</ab>
         </sp>
         <sp>
            <speaker>Augustus:</speaker>
            <ab>Thank you, Mr Hodge, I will.</ab>
         </sp>
         <stage>(Taking the drawing with him, Augustus allows himself to be shown out through the
            garden door, and Septimus follows him.)</stage>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
